Guide to the William McDougall Papers, 1892 - 1982
Duke University. University Archives
William McDougall papers 1892 - 1982
McDougall, William, 1871-1938
9.5 linear feet, Extent: 10000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
William McDougall (1871-1938), an early twentieth century psychologist, taught at Duke University from 1927 to 1938. McDougall espoused a hormic theory of psychology, emphasizing genetics and instinct over nurture. McDougall was also a strong proponent of parapsychology. The William McDougall Papers, 1892-1982, includes correspondence, writing, research, teaching materials, clippings, notebooks, photographs, diaries, drawings, and tributes. Most of the materials date from the time of McDougall's tenure at Duke University. Major subjects include Lamarckian experiments conducted by McDougall, the McDougall family (and sons Kenneth and Angus in particular), the study of parapsychology, the Parapsychology Laboratory at Duke University, the Psychology Department at Duke University, and anthropological studies in Borneo and the Torres Strait. English.
UA.29.02.0057
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The William McDougall Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1949 (A48-589), 1950 (A48-789), 1956 (A48-2339), 1967 (A67-80, A67-326), 1979 (A79-32), 1980 (A80-61, A80-80), 1985 (A85-76), 1986 (A86-31), 1990 (A90-53), and 1991 (A91-122).
Biographical Note
William McDougall, a noted psychologist, was born in Lancashire, England, in 1871. He was educated at the University of Manchester (1886-1890); St. John's College, Cambridge (M.B., 1894), St. Thomas Hospital in London; and at Oxford (M.A., 1908). He also studied at Gottingen and received the D.Sc. from the University of Manchester in 1919.
In about 1898, McDougall participated in an anthropological expedition to Borneo and the Torres Strait. Unsatisfied with anthropology, he turned back to psychology and taught at University College, London, from 1900 to 1904. From 1904 to 1920, McDougall served as a Wilde reader in mental philosophy at Oxford University. During World War I, he also served as a major in the Royal Army Medical Corps. In 1920 he became a professor of psychology at Harvard. In 1927, he came to Duke University as a professor and chair of the new Department of Psychology, a position he held until his death in 1938. McDougall was also one of the organizers of the British Psychological Society; he was for a time president of the British Society for Psychical Research; and in 1912 became a Fellow of the Royal Society of London.
McDougall was perhaps best known as a vigorous opponent of behaviorism and materialism in psychology. He strongly believed that nature, not nurture, was responsible for a person's psychological composition. Through empirical, scientific study, McDougall attempted to demonstrate that his "hormic theory of psychology," which emphasized instinct, was superior to the prevailing behaviorist theory of psychology at the time. For many years, he conducted experiments on rats to determine if training could be inherited from one generation to the next. Although his prolific writings and speeches were often controversial and unpopular, McDougall was considered one of the most prominent psychologists of his time.
He also showed a strong interest in extrasensory perception and parapsychological phenomena from his time at Oxford onward. Like his opinions on behaviorism, his advocation of parapsychology was also criticized. McDougall was instrumental in bringing J.B. Rhine to Duke University, and helping to establish the well-known Parapsychology Laboratory at the school.
In 1899, McDougall married Anne Amelia Hickmore of Brighton, England. They had five children: Leslie (Mrs. Paul Brown); Duncan Shimwell (who died while serving in the R.A.F.); Angus Dougal (who died in 1978); Kenneth Dougal (who was killed in France in World War II); and Janet Aline (who died in childhood). William McDougall died on November 28, 1938, and his widow in 1964.
Collection Overview
The William McDougall Papers date from 1892 to 1982, and contain McDougall's own papers as well as those of his family and other researchers. The collection is organized into three series. The first series, Professional, includes correspondence, writing, research, teaching materials, clippings, and tributes. Most of the materials date from the late 1920s to the late 1930s, the time of McDougall's tenure at Duke University. Of particular note is his correspondence with other scholars in the fields of psychology and the social sciences. A card file which indexes these correspondents is available with the collection. McDougall's notes from his Lamarckian experiments on rats can also be found here, as can photograph albums from his anthropological travels in the late 1890s. The Family series contains correspondence, notebooks, photographs, clippings, writings, research and education materials, diaries, drawings, and other materials. Many materials belonging to two of McDougall's sons, Kenneth and Angus, are filed here. The third series, Other Researchers, contains writings and correspondence written by other researchers about McDougall or about McDougall's influence on psychology. These materials were not directly related to or owned by McDougall; most were generated after his death.
Subject Headings
Anthropology -- Pacific Area; Diaries; Drawings; Duke University. Dept. of Psychology; Duke University. Parapsychology Laboratory; Evolutionary genetics; McDougall, Angus, 1906-1978; McDougall family; McDougall, Kenneth Dougal, 1908-; McDougall, William, 1871-1938; Parapsychology -- Research; Photographs; Psychology -- Research; Psychology -- Study and teaching (Higher); Rats as laboratory animals
Contents of Collection
- Professional, 1892-1978
  The Professional series includes correspondence, writing, research, teaching materials, clippings, and tributes. Most of the materials date from the late 1920s to the late 1930s, the time of McDougall's tenure at Duke University. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, and includes correspondence with a number of important psychologists and social sciences researchers. A card file of correspondents and subjects has been made, and is available at the Duke University Archives.
  Also in the collection are many articles written by McDougall. Many are handwritten or typescript, and may be drafts of later articles. These are arranged according to title, and are followed by a number of unidentified articles and manuscripts. Also included are bibliographies of McDougall's work.
  The research materials contains a number of notebooks kept by McDougall as he conducted Lamarckian experiments on rats at Duke University. Two photograph albums date from McDougall's early anthropological work with southeast Asian and Pacific island peoples. The Sarawak album in particular offers a unique glimpse at early 20th century life on several Pacific islands.
  The teaching materials are mainly from the 1930s and relate to Duke University. The clippings and tribute materials provide information on McDougall's influence on his contemporaries, as well as his legacy.
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - July 1931-October 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - November 1933-December 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - January 1934-September 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - October 1934-November 15, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - November 16, 1934-December 1934 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - January 1935-September 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - October 1935-December 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - January 1936-May 1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - July 1936-October 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - November 1936-December 1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - January 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - February 1937-March 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - August 1937-November 1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - December 1937-January 1938 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - February 1938-June 1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - July 1938-November 1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Writings (Box 3)
    - Anthropology and History (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - The British in the Far East (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - The Conduct of Life (handwritten)
      - Pages 1-150 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Pages 151-300 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Pages 301-460 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Appendix (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Envelope with notes (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Cutaneous Sensations (reprint) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Duke University Institute for Child Study (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - The Energies of Men (second revision), 1932 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Family Allowances, Birth Control, and Eugenics (handwritten and typescript) (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Fourth Report on a Lamarckian Experiment (reprint), January 1938 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Notes on The Group Mind (typescript) (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Health and Continual Youth (handwritten and typescript) (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Health and Continual Youth (handwritten) (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Health and Continual Youth (handwritten) (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - How Sambo Was Trained (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Japan or America--an open letter to H.I.M. the Emperor of Japan (handwritten) (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - The 'Margery Mediumship' (reprint), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Mechanism and Purpose (handwritten) (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Mechanism, Purpose, and the New Freedom (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Mechanism, Purpose, and the New Freedom (reprint), 1934 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Mental Evolution (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Modern Materialism (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Modern Materialism (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Notes to Modern Materialism (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - The Nature of Emotion (typescript) (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - The Nature of Emotion (reprint), 1933 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - New Light on Laughter (reprint) (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - A Note on Suggestion (reprint), 1920 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Notes on his terminal illness (handwritten and typescript), circa 1938 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Of the Words Character and Personality (handwritten and typescript) (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Parapsychology (handwritten) (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Pareto as a Psychologist (reprint), October 1935 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Philosophy and the Social Sciences (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - The Philosophy of J.S. Haldane (reprint), October 1936 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Psychical Research as a University Study (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Psychoanalysis and Social Psychology (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Recent Tendencies of German Psychology (handwritten) (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Relations Between Dissociation and Repression (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Religion and the Sciences of Life (reprint), 1932 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - The 'Reverse Picture' in Telepathy (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Review of Max Eastman's Enjoyment of Laughter (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - The Rival Schools of Psychology (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - The Role of Experiment in Psychology (handwritten) (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Scope and Method of Social Psychology (handwritten) (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Should All Taboos Be Abolished? (typescript) (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Some New Observations in Support of Thomas Young's Theory... (reprint) (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - A Theory of Muscular Contraction (reprint) (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Unidentified manuscripts (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 67-71)
    - Notebooks (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 72-74)
    - Bibliographies, 1939-1943 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Publisher Information, 1932, undated (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Reviews of McDougall's publications (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Research
    - Duke University Experiments
      These experiments were McDougall's Lamarckian research with rats.
      - Volume I, September 1928-May 1930 (Box 7, Folder 78)
      - Volume II, December 1929-February 1932 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - Volume III, February 1932-February 1933 (Box 7, Folder 80)
      - Volume IV, circa January 1934 (Box 7, Folder 81)
      - Volume V, circa November 1935 (Box 7, Folder 82)
      - Unnumbered Volume, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 83)
      - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - F. Kenneth Girdlestone notebook on parapsychology, circa 1916 (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Notebooks
      - circa 1924 (Box 8, Folder 86)
      - September 1927-September 1928 (Box 8, Folder 87)
      - Undated (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - Notes on Paralysis in Fowls, undated (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - Photo Album, circa 1892-1900--Located in Oversized Materials, Box 15 (Box 8)
      This album contains pictures from McDougall's days at Oxford, as well as some of his research travels to Asia.
    - Photo Album, Sarawak, circa 1900--Located in Oversized Materials, Box 15 (Box 8)
      This album contains pictures from McDougall's travels to the Pacific Island of Sarawak. The photographs appear to be platinum prints of the islanders, their villages, and their work, warfare, and cultural events. The album is inscribed, "For W McDougall with complements from R Shelford and Charles Hove."
  - Teaching
    - Class Notes and Syllabus for Social Psychology, undated (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Psychology Department
      The Psychology Department subseries refers to the Duke University Department of Psychology.
      - 1934-1935 (Box 8, Folder 91)
      - 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - Budget, 1932-1935 (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - Ph.D. Candidates, circa 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Ph.D. Examinations, undated (Box 9, Folder 95)
      - Ph.D. Preliminaries circa 1934 (Box 9, Folder 96)
      - Ph.D. Research Proposals, undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Student Papers
      - A-D (Box 9, Folder 98)
      - E-F (Box 9, Folder 99)
      - H-P (Box 9, Folder 100)
      - P (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Clippings
    - About McDougall's career, 1925-1937 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Collected by McDougall, circa 1930-1938 (Box 10, Folder 104-105)
    - Obituaries of McDougall, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Tributes to McDougall, 1938-1978 (Box 10, Folder 107)
- Family, 1901-1978
  The Family series contains correspondence, notebooks, photographs, clippings, writings, research and education materials, diaries, drawings, and other materials. The family kept notebooks in which observations on the children's development were recorded, and included in this series is a notebook for each child except for Kenneth. A significant number of family photographs are also included in this series, and have been sorted according to subject.
  A major portion of the series is devoted to materials belonging to two of the McDougall children, Kenneth and Angus. Kenneth continued working on his father's Lamarckian experiments after William McDougall's death in 1938, and his research notebooks are included. Also included in his papers are his armed forces documents, correspondence with his mother during his service in World War II, and diaries kept in the late 1930s. In the Angus McDougall subseries, copies of drawings of Perkins Library, made in 1969, are included, along with correspondence and writings.
  - Clippings, circa 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Correspondence
    - 1920-1925 (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - 1930-1944 (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Condolence, 1938-1939 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Funeral Announcements and Programs, circa 1938-1978 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Notebooks
    - Angus McDougall, circa 1906-1914 (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - Duncan McDougall, circa 1906-1917 (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Janet McDougall, circa 1912-1914 (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - Leslie McDougall, circa 1901 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Pedigree (Genealogy), undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Photographs
    - William McDougall (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Anne (Mrs. William) McDougall (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - Children of William and Anne McDougall (Box 11, Folder 120-121)
    - Other People (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Sculptures by Angus McDougall (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Wellwick House (McDougall home in England), 1961 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Kenneth McDougall
    - Armed Forces Materials, 1943-1944 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - Biographical Profile, undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Correspondence
      - 1939-1941 (Box 12, Folder 127)
      - 1942 (Box 12, Folder 128)
      - 1943 (Box 12, Folder 129)
      - 1944 (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - Diary - Lunga Island, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Diary - Appalachian Trail, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - Education
      - Diplomas and Certificates, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 133)
      - Invertebrates, 1938-1941, undated (Box 12, Folder 134)
      - Invertebrates, undated (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Surgery II Notebook, undated (Box 13, Folder 136)
      - Zoology, 1939-1940 (Box 13, Folder 137)
      - Zoology, 1941-1942 (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Lamarckian Experiments notebooks--Located in Oversized Materials, Box 16
      - 1938-1940 (Box 13)
      - November 1940 (Box 13)
      - Undated (Box 13)
    - Research Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Writings, 1941, undated (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Writings - Poems, undated (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - Angus McDougall
    - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - Drawings, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - Writings - Published Poetry, 1971-1975 (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Writings, undated (Box 13, Folder 145)
- Other Researchers, 1919-1982
  The Other Researchers series contains writings and correspondence written by other researchers about McDougall or about McDougall's influence on psychology. These materials were not directly related to or owned by McDougall; most were generated after his death. The series is arranged in alphabetical order by researcher name.
  - Bhupendra Chandra Kar: The Psychology of Prof. William McDougall with its Bearing on Education (dissertation), undated (Box 14, Folder 146)
  - Harold McCurdy
    - Correspondence
      - Bevan, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 147)
      - Boden, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 148)
      - Geinitz, 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 149)
      - Jones, 1977-1980 (Box 14, Folder 150)
      - Kastenbaum, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 151)
      - Krantz, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 152)
      - Leary, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 153)
      - Lubek, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 154)
      - McGraw-Hill, 1969-1975 (Box 14, Folder 155)
      - Newbold and related, 1978-1980 (Box 14, Folder 156)
      - Rhine, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Paper, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Lewis F. Richardson: Mathematical Psychology of War, 1919 (Box 14, Folder 159)
- Oversize Materials
  - Photo Album, circa 1892-1900 (Box 15)
  - Photo Album, Sarawak, circa 1900 (Box 15)
  - Lamarckian Experiments notebooks (Box 16)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 16)
    - November 1940 (Box 16)
    - Undated (Box 16)
Related Material
Department of Psychology Records
Duke University Archives
Parapsychology Laboratory Records
Rare Books, Manuscripts, and Special Collections Department, Duke University
Bibliography
Sally Jean Newbold, William McDougall, M.D., F.R.S., "A Psychologist in Changing Times", 1985.
Jane Gentry Smith, The mystery of the mind: a biography of William McDougall, 1985.